Today's דף *daf* is יא *Yud Aleph* 11. We pick up at
the bottom of י עמוד ב *Yud Amud Bet*. We had just
seen a whole question about whether רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda*
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* debate whether the donkey is
forbidden in benefit, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says it's
not. Then there's a debate of אמוראים Amoraim. *Amoraim* seems to be
even a conflict of the ברייתות Braitos *Braitas* משניות Mishnayos *Mishnas* etc.
whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* would admit after the neck
is broken. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* picks up, it had also
mentioned an issue about how is it possible that the donkey even
if it is forbidden in benefit you cannot use it to marry
a woman, isn't there some value you get by redeeming it by
a cheaper sheep? So there will always be some value that you
can get from it. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, this
could be the opinion of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה *Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda* that says that the sheep can be no less than a
שקל shekel *shekel*. And since it can't be less than a שקל
shekel. *shekel*, you could have a scenario where the donkey is a
שקל shekel. *shekel* or less than a שקל shekel. *shekel* that you
will get no benefit by redeeming it by the sheep. So we
pick up with that and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
אמר מר *Amar Mar*, 1 2 3 6 7 lines from the
bottom, 4 lines before the end of the line, 4 lines right
above where it says תפדה *Tifdeh* in brackets at the beginning of
the line. אמר מר *Amar Mar*, so we had just said, תפדה
תפדה
*Tifdeh Tifdeh*, it says you shall redeem it twice in two separate
פסוקים *pesukim*. תפדה מיד *Tifdeh miyad*, one is to tell you you
can do it immediately. תפדה כל שהוא *Tifdeh kol shehu*, the other
is that it can have even close to no value, which is
not רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה *Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda* who demands that
it be worth a שקל shekel *shekel*. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says פשיטא pishita *peshita*, obviously you can do it immediately. No, איצטריך
*itztarich*, סלקא דעתך אמינא salka dachach amina *salka daitach amina*, I might
have thought, since it says you should redeem the firstborn of human
and redeem the firstborn of donkeys, so it puts them together in
the same פסוק pasuk *pasuk* and they're both redeemed. So I might
have thought, מה בכור אדם אחר שלשים וחמש *ma bechor adam achar
shloshim v'chamesh* has to be after 30 days and has to be
5 שקלים shekalim, *shekalim*, so האי נמי אחר שלשים וחמש *hai nami
achar shloshim v'chamesh* maybe here too it has to be after 30
days and has to be 5 שקל *shekel*. Not necessarily with the
sheep, but maybe it means that if I didn't do a sheep
I should do 5 שקל *shekel*, or maybe it means that the
sheep has to be a minimum worth 5 שקל *shekel*, maybe I
should learn this out from human. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
*kamashma lan*, תפדה מיד *Tifdeh miyad* you can redeem it right away,
you do not have to wait for the donkey for 30 days.
תפדה כל שהוא *Tifdeh kol shehu* and even if the sheep is
a כל שהוא *kol shehu*. We said before we're going to say
again that if you do it with a non-sheep, then it has
to be value, but the sheep could be worth even close to
nothing. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר אין פדיה פחות משקל *Rabbi Yose
b'Rabbi Yehuda omer ein pidya pachot mi'shekel*. The redemption, you cannot redeem
something for less than a שקל *shekel*. Where does he know this
from? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ממה נפשך *mimah nafshach*, make
up your mind. אי מקיש בכור אדם *i makish bechor adam* if
you compare it to humans, so חמש איבעי *chamesh iba'ei* you should
do 5 שקלים *shekalim*, that's what we know you do with humans'
firstborn. ואי לא מקיש *v'i lo makish* and if you don't connect
it, שקל מנא ליה *shekel minalei* where do you get the idea
of a שקל *shekel* altogether? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לעולם
לא מקיש *l'olam lo makish*. We don't connect it to humans, he
never mentioned humans. So אמר רבה אמר קרא *Amar Rabba Amar Kra*
where does he get the idea that the sheep has to be
worth at least a שקל *shekel*? Because the verse says וכל ערכך
יהיה בשקל הקדש hekdesh, *v'chol erkecha yihyeh b'shekel hakodesh*. This is at
the end of ספר ויקרא *Sefer Vayikra*,
and there it says that if you have sanctified something, you said
the ערך *erech*, the value of a certain person is upon me,
so the תורה Torah *Torah* there gives you a chart based on
gender and based on age, it tells you how much is the
fixed ערך *erech* for a certain person. And it ends by saying
all of your ערך *erech* should be with the שקל *shekel*. Now
why does it have to say that? It already said this person
is 5 שקל *shekel*, this is 20, this is 30. What's the
point? So he understands that that's telling you the following principle. כל
ערכין שאתה מעריך *kol erchin she'ata maarich* anytime you do any estimation
of value for the sake of redemption, now of course it's a
little funny there it wasn't exactly redemption, but nevertheless, any type of
estimation of value where the money is, and also it's not exactly
the same you should also realize because there it's going to the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, here it's not going to the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, it's going to a כהן Kohen
*Kohen* and it doesn't become sanctified. But nevertheless, we're learning out from
there that any similar type of a thing of
evaluating and of transferring status, some type of a ritual of redemption,
לא יפחתו משקל *lo yifchatu mi'shekel* cannot be less than a שקל
*shekel*. Okay, so that's where he learned it out from. ורבנן *V'rabbanan*,
what would the Rabbis say back? ההוא *Hahu*, that verse is not
teaching you that. What is that verse for? להשיג יד *L'hasig yad*,
specifically within that פרשה *parsha* of ערכין *erchin* that somebody says I
will give the ערך *erech* of this individual upon me, but let's
say the person is poor. So he accepted upon him the ערך
*erech* and now he has to give 20 שקל *shekel*, 30 שקל
*shekel*, he doesn't have that. So the תורה *Torah* actually ends by
saying, it says על פי אשר תשיג יד הנודר *al pi asher
tasig yad hanoder* after telling you what the fixed values are, it
says based on what the person can afford. So what is it?
Is it a fixed value or is it based on what the
person can afford? So the answer is yes, it's a fixed value
if he can afford it. But if he can't afford it, then
you sort of reduce the value to something that is affordable by
that person. Okay, you tweak the value so the person can afford
it if you have to reduce it down, and for that we
say it can't be less than a שקל *shekel*. וכל ערכך יהיה
בשקל הקדש hekdesh. *v'chol erkecha yihyeh b'shekel hakodesh*, even if he can't
afford a שקל *shekel*, I'm sorry, you can't set the value at
less than a שקל *shekel*. That's where
the
פסוק *pasuk* is written specifically within the... Thank you so much. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman
*Amar Rav Nachman*, הלכה halacha, כדברי חכמים Chachamim *halacha k'divrei
chachamim*. We rule like the
חכמים *chachamim* that it does not have to be a שקל *shekel*,
it can be even a כל שהוא *kol shehu*, even close to
nothing. So of course the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, like it classically does,
says וכמה *v'chama*? Okay, so what's the minimum? After saying it doesn't
have to be a שקל *shekel* and it can be anything, so
we want to say, okay, but what is the minimum? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*, אפילו פטרוזא
בר דנקא *afilu patruza bar danka*, even a skinny scrawny sheep, which
is apparently what the word פטרוזא *patruza* means, worth a דנקא *danka*,
which is a sixth of a זוז zuz. *zuz*. So again, one
imagines that even that is לאו דוקא *lav davka*.
Even less than a חד גדיא *chad
gadya* we buy on פסח *Pesach*. There you go, that's good. חד
גדיא *Chad gadya* that אבא *Abba* bought with תרי זוזי *t'rei zuzei*.
Okay, anyway, so anyway, even presumably it really doesn't matter how bad,
how sickly the sheep is or how cheap it is, really anything.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, פשיטא *pshita*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, אף אנן נמי תנינא *af anan
nami tanina*, that's implicit in our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*, because our משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* says גדול וקטן *gadol v'katan*, it could be big or
small, so it doesn't really matter, whatever you want. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, פשיטא *pshita*, yeah obviously that's already in our משנה
mishna. *Mishnah*, it's not so פשיטא *pshita*, you wouldn't have needed רבא
*Rava* to have made, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* to have made the
point to begin with. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, no, מהו
דתימא *mahu d'teima*, I might have thought כולי האי לא *kulei hai
lo*, even when our משנה mishna, *Mishnah* says big or small, just
like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* originally asked, okay, but how small? So
first of all, don't tell me just because it says small you
would have said even a completely trivial amount, you know, you would
have said, you might have put a lower limit on it. Number
one. אינמי *Inami*, or פטרוזא *patruza* לא *lo*, you might have said
its value can be close to nothing, but it has to be
a good healthy sheep. Meaning if it's like a firstborn sheep and
it's a good healthy sheep, maybe it could be very low value,
but if it's scrawny and you know sickly, then maybe that's not
appropriate, not just because of the value but because of, you know,
the way it looks, the quality of it. So and so therefore
we are emphasizing that even though the משנה mishna *Mishnah* says big
or small, we really mean it could be as cheap as possible
and it could be as in bad condition as possible. Okay, the
only thing it can't be is dead, which we'll get to. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, now we're going to
get to some practical הלכה halacha *halacha* about this. So, רב יהודה
נשיאה *Rav Yehuda Nesia*, רב יהודה נשיאה *Rav Yehuda Nesia*, not to
be confused with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda הנשיא *Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi*, רב
יהודה נשיאה *Rav Yehuda Nesia* was the grandson of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda, הנשיא *Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi*. Okay, so רב יהודה נשיאה *Rav Yehuda
Nesia*,
so he was already in the period of the אמוראים Amoraim *Amoraim*.
So רב יהודה נשיאה *Rav Yehuda Nesia*, הוה ליה פטר חמור peter
chamor. *havlei peter chamor*, he had a firstborn donkey. So שדר לקמיה
דרב טרפון *shadar l'kamei d'Rav Tarfon*, he sent it to רב טרפון
Rav Tarfon *Rav Tarfon*. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, כמה בעינא למיתב לכהן
*kama ba'ina l'meisav l'kohen*? How much do I have to give to
the כהן Kohen. *kohen*? Now presumably based on the previous context and
what we're going to say afterwards, he means if I'm going to
redeem with a sheep, how expensive of a sheep do I need
to use? It's quite funny that it says he sent a donkey.
Yeah, I don't know, that is quite strange. Maybe he thought, maybe
he didn't know the הלכה halacha *halacha* or whatever, you know, whatever.
Well, yeah, I know, so maybe I shouldn't have said it that
way. So maybe there was a question as to what the הלכה
halacha. *halacha* was. Maybe he thought
that the, what do you call it, that, you know, that there
would be some sense of, I mean I think intuitively I would
have thought this. You could tell me it could be even a
small sheep, even you know a cheap sheep. But first of all,
you would figure a sheep should be a little respectable in terms
of quality and value. But the other thing you might think is,
if it's a very expensive donkey, maybe you have a responsibility to
upgrade also the sheep, you know, that it be somewhat proportionate. Maybe
it doesn't have to be the value of the sheep. So maybe
that was implicitly what the question was. Here's this gorgeous donkey I
have, who knows, maybe a special breed or something, what's my obligation?
Okay, so he wanted him to see the donkey to make sure
he was getting the full answer.
If he sees a donkey worth a hundred dollars, he can't give
the כהן kohen *kohen* ninety dollars.
Not ninety dollars, but he can give the כהן kohen. *kohen* a
sheep that's worth two dollars. That's what we've been saying.
The sheep, he can give that as a replacement.
Yes, that's what we've been saying for the last few days. The,
if you use a sheep, the sheep can be much, much less
than the donkey. And that's maybe what we're saying is maybe a
little bit of what he was asking. Not only what's the minimum
value of the sheep have to be, but does it to some
degree have to be proportionate to the value of the donkey? Maybe
that's why he sent the donkey to him. So let's see what
he said. So let's see what the answer was.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, אמר ליה *amar lei*,
he said back to him, so he says אמר ליה *amar lei*,
he said back to him, הרי אמרו *harei amru*, they said, עין
יפה בסלע *ayin yafa b'sela*, a generous person will give a סלע
selah. *sela*, עין רעה בשקל *ayin ra b'shekel*, a stingy
person will give a שקל *shekel*, ובינוני *u'veinoni*, and an average person
will give ברגייא *bargaya*. I've never heard ברגייא *bargaya* before, but anyway,
it is, a שקל *shekel* is a half of a סלע selah,
*sela*, and a ברגייא *bargaya* is three quarters of a סלע *sela*.
Okay, so it's exactly midpoint between a שקל *shekel* and a סלע
*sela*. Yes.
Artscroll vocalizes
it as ברגייא *birgiya*. ברגייא *Birgiya*?
ברגייא *Birgiya*, yeah. Okay, all right. Okay, anyway, so אמר רבא *amar
Rava*, הלכתא ברגייא *hilchasa birgiya*, that's what we rule, that you should
give that amount. וכמה *V'kama*? And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* also
had a turn about that money before. So it said תלתא זוזי
*tlata zuzei*, three זוז zuz. *zuz*, because a שקל *shekel* is four
זוז *zuz*, a סלע *sela*, excuse me, שקל *shekel* is two, a
סלע *sela* is four. Before, this is exactly in the middle. And
now it seems like it's trying to actually do a mnemonic out
of this word בריגיה. Barigya. Now not exactly clear whether that was
actually the name of the coin or that was just a phrase
used. Anyway, רגיל הכא ורגיל הכא. ragil hacha v'ragil hacha. It's halfway
here, halfway there, meaning it's exactly midpoint between a שקל and a
סלע. It is three זוז. Okay, that's what you should give. That's
at least the average. Now presumably רבי ינאי מסיאה, Rabbi Yannai Mi-Si'ah,
they were pretty wealthy, so hopefully he had gave actually the סלע,
not just בריגיה. But it's interesting that רב טרפון Rav Tarfon did
not tell him you have to give the highest amount. He actually
told him, here's your range. Okay, now someone asked about שמואל.
Shmuel. They said the same thing, right?
What'd they say? I understand. Yeah, I mean there is a range.
Yes, I'm just saying that if you're asking me, I might say,
well, here's the range, but since you're rich, you should give the
top of it. Now maybe he did say that. Maybe just for
our sake we're being told that here is the practical הלכה, halacha
here is the range. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, קשיא הלכתא
אהלכתא. kashya hilcheta a-hilcheta. One minute, we have a problem now about
our rulings because before we said that we ruled like the חכמים
that we said even a sixth of a דינר, dinar, like you
know, which is a completely trivial amount. Here we're saying it should
be between two and four זוז. So make up your mind, which
is it? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא. lo kashya. It's
not difficult. כאן דבא לימלך כאן דעושה מעצמו. kan d'ba limalech kan
d'oseh me'atzmo. One is you're asking advice, the other is you're doing
it on your own. If you're doing it on your own and
you do it even for like a scrawny, totally almost worthless sheep,
it works. Anything works. If you're asking our advice, we're going to
tell you what's appropriate. Okay, so what's appropriate is sort of like,
and as Michael says, it's very parallel to the idea of תרומה.
terumah. תרומה terumah we say that בדיעבד b'di'eved if you do even
one grain, you can exempt an entire store warehouse full of grain
even with like one tiny little grain. תרומה terumah can be the
smallest amount. But if you ask us what are our guidelines, our
guidelines are a fortieth, a fiftieth, a sixtieth based on whether you're
generous, cheap, or average. So the same type of point here. Yes.
פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen you give five שקל.
פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen there's no fooling around.
The כהן kohen can be שווה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. What?
But it doesn't matter what the object is, but it has to
be worth five שקל. Value of five. Yes, yes. But here the
sheep doesn't matter how much it's worth.
Five
for the coin?
No, no, no. It's not about the coins. It's about the value.
Yeah, yeah. Yes.
He has Artscroll says that רב טרפון was כהן. Kohen So I
don't know.
Oh, yeah, I was going to ask. Okay, that's a nice point.
So maybe they want to be נוגע בדבר. noge'ah b'davar. He didn't
want to give him advice exactly what to do. He gave him
the range. That's a good point. Okay, and weren't we saying
that
like you can give more? You can give a sheep that's worth
more than the donkey, yes.
But for פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen you can give them five שקלים,
you can give them ten שקל.
Well,
you can give whatever you want, but the rest will just be
a gift. It won't count as the פדיון. pidyon. The פדיון pidyon
is no less and no more than five שקל for פדיון הבן.
Pidyon HaBen.
Yes. But we were saying that like some people, you know, that
one way of interpreting was you can even, you know, do it
with a sheep, right?
Yeah, we're going to get to that. Okay, but here the assumption,
but here, but if you're going to do the actual value, it
has to be the exact value. He would not have given him
a range.
They're not just giving him the פטר חמור.
That is an option.
You can give it.
Yes, but it's an option. תורה says you have to redeem it.
What do you want me to do?
You can redeem it with another donkey of equal value.
Right, which would be kind of funny. That's true. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. אמר רב יצחק אמר ריש לקיש. Amar Rav Yitzchak amar Reish
Lakish. So רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak said, אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish
Lakish, מי שיש לו פטר חמור ואין לו שה לפדותו, mi she-yesh
lo peter chamor v'ein lo seh lifdoto, if you have a donkey
and you don't have a
sheep, פודהו בשוויו. podehu b'shavyo. You can actually redeem it with the
value. This is an idea we said before, but again, it's fascinating.
This is an idea that's only articulated at the period of the
אמוראים. amoraim The משניות and ברייתות never mentioned value. They only mention
using a sheep. But the אמוראים actually say, no, you know what?
Actually sheep is an option. Sheep makes it easy for you so
you don't need to do the value. But you can always redeem
with value itself.
Wait, so שוויו shavyo means the value of the donkey.
Okay, that you cannot be as little as you want. It has
to be the value of the donkey if you're not doing a
sheep.
But then we'll say you can do the value of a scrawny
Correct, correct. It's either a sheep regardless of value or the value
of the donkey. So let's take a look. למאן? L'man? According to
whom are you saying this? אילימא לרבי יהודה? Ilima l'Rabbi Yehuda? If
you say רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. הא אמר הקפידה עליו תורה בשה?
ha amar hikpida alav Torah b'seh? If you remember, one of רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda. arguments why we should assume the donkey is forbidden
in benefit is because there was a ritual of redemption. And the
proof that there's a ritual is that it has to be a
sheep. And the גמרא Gemara later qualified that and said, no, maybe
he would admit that you could also do value, its equivalent value
if you didn't use a sheep. But at least the way it
was initially articulated was the ritual requires specifically a sheep. So that
sounded like there's no alternatives to a sheep. Okay, so if it's
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, didn't he say that it has to be
a sheep? And that was his proof that there was a ritual
and that therefore it was forbidden in benefit and so on. So
it can't be you're saying this according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda,
So the גמרא gemara says like
this. אלא לרבי שמעון? Ela l'Rabbi Shimon? It sounds like you're saying
it according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says it's not forbidden
in benefit and therefore you could do a sheep, you could do
value, you have a lot of options. So רב אחא מתני הכי.
Rav Acha masni hachi. That's what רב אחא Rav Acha taught. But
then רבינא קשיא ליה. Ravina kashya leh. רבינא Ravina had a question.
What do you mean that he's telling ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
telling Giving me a הלכה halacha. *halacha* according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon*. Right now ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* told us a הלכה *halacha*
you can do value, it doesn't have to be sheep, and we're
saying that really only works according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* would demand a sheep. But one minute, that means
you're implicitly ruling like רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. And now we get
to the question: who do we rule like about it being forbidden
in benefit, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* or רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*? So
here's what רבינא *Ravina*'s difficulty was: רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* versus רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, הלכה כרבי יהודה *halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda*. First of all,
we have a general ruling. If there's a debate of רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, we rule like רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*. That's one of the כללים klalim *klalim*, number one. Number
two, סתם לן תנא כרבי יהודה *stam l'an tana k'Rabbi Yehuda*. Our
משנה *mishna* is רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. Why is our סתם משנה
*stam mishna* like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*? Because our משנה *mishna* said
what do you do if you have a doubtful firstborn donkey? You
redeem it and you keep the sheep. And the גמרא *Gemara* said,
why bother redeeming it if you're going to keep it? And the
גמרא *Gemara* interestingly, and we pointed this out, didn't say well there's
a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to redeem it. No, the גמרא *Gemara* said
the only reason you would redeem it if you're going to keep
it in the end is if it's forbidden in benefit and you
want to make it no longer forbidden in benefit. So the only
reason to redeem a doubtful firstborn donkey is if you rule like
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and say that before it's redeemed it's forbidden
in benefit. So in case it might be firstborn, you want to
get rid of that problem. Okay, so since our משנה *mishna* says
you redeem it when it's doubtful, it would only make sense according
to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* that says that it's forbidden in benefit
and if that's the case you want to remove that problem. So
therefore, not only number one, in general we rule like רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* over רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, number two, our משנה *mishna*
implicitly rules like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* because our משנה *mishna* says
redeem it when it's a doubt and that would be to remove
its forbidden status. So how can you, ואת אמרת הלכה כרבי שמעון
*v'at amarta halacha k'Rabbi Shimon*? You're saying you can redeem it with
its value, which is a הלכה *halacha* that only makes sense according
to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. How could you say that? Obviously we
rule like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. אלא *Ela*, you know what? אפילו
תימא רבי יהודה *Afilu teima Rabbi Yehuda*. This ruling of ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish* really works according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* as well.
Why? That even רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* who emphasizes that there's a
ritual of redeeming with the sheep, he would admit that you could
also redeem with value. Why? לא יהא חמור מן man ההקדש *Lo
yehei chamur min hahekdesh*. I don't know if there's a pun with
the word חמור *chamur* there.
It should not be any worse than הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*. Why should
it be no worse than הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*? Because when if you
sanctify my house or my car, I can redeem it with its
value, and certainly even there, certainly if the my car is sanctified,
it's forbidden in benefit, there's מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah*, there's a lot of
status of הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh* status on my car. And even when
there's a lot of status on that, I can transfer the status
with value. So if I can do it by הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*,
which certainly has a lot of status, certainly I could do it
with a donkey that's forbidden in benefit. One minute, and though the
Torah says ואמר תורה בשה *v'amar Torah b'seh*, when the Torah says
sheep, it was not saying להחמיר *l'hachmir*, to make life more difficult
for you, to demand that it must be a sheep, אלא להקל
*ela l'hakel*, to make it easier for you, to say if you
don't want to do the full value, you can always just do
a sheep instead. So based on the comparison of—and in a way,
if you actually think about it, it's funny the גמרא *Gemara* is
inclined to say that according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* it's less
likely to say value, because if anything, I would have said the
opposite. I would have said for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that there
is no status of the donkey, it's not forbidden in benefit, then
the whole thing is just a ritual. Right? Whereas according to רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, where the donkey is forbidden in benefit, then it
is more similar to the idea of הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* where you
can transfer the status and where you can use something of its
value, and it's not just a ritual, it's an actual act of
substitution. But anyway, the גמרא *Gemara* thinks that it's more obvious according
to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* because of the language used before by
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, but at the end of the day, we
say that it's true according to both opinions. So whether רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* or רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, they all agree that when
the sheep is an option, it could be even a cheap sheep
(try to say that five times fast), a very inexpensive sheep, but
it could also be the value if you don't want to use
the sheep, the equivalent value also works. And in terms of how
we rule, it's very clear we rule like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*:
the donkey is forbidden in benefit before you redeem it. If you
went ahead and broke its neck, it's certainly forbidden in benefit afterwards,
although there was a debate what רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* would hold
about that. And that we have said also
that—what do you call it? And we've said now, redeem it with
a sheep even of almost no value, but if you ask our
advice, we'll tell you between a range of a שקל *shekel* and
a סלע *sela*.
And finally, that if you don't want to use a sheep, you
can do it of any object as long as it's of equivalent
value. Charlie, you had a point.
Some things when you redeem them, you have to pay more than
the value?
A fifth more, yeah. That we're not suggesting. That's a good point,
and here you're the owner. So why don't we say add a
fifth? Right, so again, the גמרא *Gemara* is not going that far
in the comparison. It's not even quoting פסוקים *psukim* to make the
comparison, right? So, and again here even if it's forbidden in benefit,
it's not like
הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh*. There, the money actually does become sanctified, it does
go to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. So it is a good
question, who told us to make the comparison this far but not
all the way, you know? But I guess the גמרא *Gemara* is
saying there's something intuitive about redeeming something with its value. To say
that you add a fifth, we'll limit ourselves to when the Torah
actually demands that. But that's a very good question.
Yes, I agree. And רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*'s position seems to make
a lot of sense. Why do we not rule like him? Why
do we do a case-by-case basis?
Well, we do sometimes. The כללי הפסק *klalei hapsak* are only general
כללים *klalim*, they're not absolute rules. Number one, so if there's an
exception, we will. Why exactly that is an excellent question which I
do not have a good answer for. Who decided what the כללים
were and what are the כללים based on, like we know בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, at least there was a
בת קול, bat kol, but in general, who says הלכה כרבי עקיבא
מחברו ולא מרבו? halacha ke-Rabbi Akiva me-chavero ve-lo me-rabo?
Yeah, that is a very, very good, you have to assume that
there was some consensus that grew up about those types of things.
Exactly what the nature of that consensus was, I don't know. Why
do we go like the בבלי Bavli and not like the ירושלמי?
Yerushalmi? You know, so a lot of the questions about in the
end, which has which sort of works and positions and you know,
rabbis and תנאים tannaim and אמוראים have authority, a lot of that
is a function of a consensus that develops, not necessarily a logical
position, then you could ask how did that consensus come about, and
that's more of a historical question. I'm sure there was some logic
to it, but it's that's a really excellent question.
Yeah. And there are exceptions. On שבת Shabbos law we follow
רבי שמעון over רבי יהודה. Right, right, we don't
right, that's what I said to Michael, it is not a hard
and fast rule, it is just a general guideline. Okay, so now
the גמרא goes on, let's take a look.
Now going to have some case law. Okay, רב נחמן בריה דרב
יצחק, Rav Nachman brei de-Rav Yitzchak, רב נחמן Rav Nachman the son
of רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, פריק ליה בשוקי. parik leh be-shuki.
We mentioned this before, he redeemed his donkey with קוקתא kukta herbs
בשוה, be-shaveh, as long as it was worth equivalent to the value
of the donkey itself. אמר רב שיזבי אמר רב הונא,
Amar Rav Shizbi amar
Rav Huna, רב שיזבי Rav Shizbi said in the name of רב
הונא, Rav Huna, הפודה פטר חמור של חברו, ha-podeh peter chamor shel
chavero, and now we are getting to the concept of looking at
it like הקדש, hekdesh, right here we're suggesting something that never would
have occurred to us. Charlie here has a firstborn donkey, I say,
I give my sheep to the כהן Kohen, in exchange for Charlie's
firstborn donkey. I'm going to do Charlie a favor
and
redeem the donkey with the sheep, it'll be my sheep, Charlie didn't
even ask me, but because no good deed goes and that wouldn't
work, because I don't do anything for free, really, after I redeem
it, I'm going to try to actually ask that I get Charlie's
donkey. Now if that actually was the הלכה it would be absurd
because since you can do a cheap, a very inexpensive sheep for
an expensive donkey, everybody would be roaming around with their sheep waiting
to see whose firstborn donkey so they can redeem somebody else's donkey
and get the donkey.
Well, doesn't the owner have the option of doing it first?
Well, we're not even saying that. So let's take a look. Anyway,
first of all, the very fact that somebody else can do it
is something that has to have been inferred or learned from other
areas of הקדש. hekdesh, If I sanctify my car, somebody else can
redeem it and give the money to the בית המקדש and get
my car. So you know, already this question about are we making
this its own self-contained ritual or how much are we trying to
analogize it to other cases? Although again, the irony here is that
it is not analogous because the donkey is forbidden in benefit but
the sheep is not. So the status does not really transfer. But
anyway, we're clearly creating some type of implicit comparison and we have
we start by assuming that somebody else can redeem my donkey. Not
just as my שליח, shaliach, on their own. So let's take a
look.
הפודה פטר חמור של חברו, ha-podeh peter chamor shel chavero, פדיונו פדוי.
pidyono paduy. So first it starts with that ruling. If somebody redeems
my donkey, it works and that sheep now belongs to the כהן.
Kohen And he gets to keep the donkey?
Well, that's the next question. בעו ליה, Bayu leh, then they raise
the question. פדיונו לפודה או פדיונו לבעלים? pidyono la-podeh o pidyono la-be'alim?
Does the redeemer get to keep the donkey or does the owner
get to keep the donkey? As I said, it would be pretty
crazy societally to rule that the owner, that without my permission you
can redeem my donkey and keep my donkey. So the גמרא says
like this, אליבא דרבי שמעון לא תיבעי לך. aliba de-Rabbi Shimon lo
teba'e lach. According to רבי שמעון that the donkey is not forbidden
in benefit, there's no question that you do not get to keep
my donkey.
כיון דאמר מותר בהנאה, keivan de-amar mutar be-hana'ah, since even before it
was redeemed I could get benefit from my donkey, ממונא דבעלים הוא.
mamona de-be'alim hu. It's completely mine even before it was redeemed. So
how does you deciding to give a sheep for me give title
to my donkey? My donkey wasn't out of my hands to begin
with. I could always derive benefit. I just had a מצוה mitzvah,
to do. You wanted to do my מצוה, mitzvah, געזונטהייט gezunteheit and
spend your money, געזונטהייט, gezunteheit, but it was just a מצוה, mitzvah
it was nothing that would entitle you to the donkey, it was
fully mine to begin with. Okay, so כי תיבעי לך, ki teba'e
lach, what's our question? כי תיבעי לך אליבא דרבי יהודה. ki teba'e
lach aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda. According to רבי יהודה, דאמר אסור בהנאה. de-amar
assur be-hana'ah. Before I redeemed it, I did not have rights to
it. It was forbidden in benefit. So the donkey was out of
my hands, as it were, before it was redeemed. So להקדש מדמי
ליה, le-hekdesh medami leh, is it therefore like something I had sanctified?
ורחמנא אמר ונתן הכסף וקם לו, ve-rachmana amar ve-natan ha-kesef ve-kam lo,
you give the money and it becomes and it gets, it stands
for you, meaning whoever redeems, once I sanctify my car, if Charlie
comes and redeems my car, he gets to keep it. He goes
home, drives home with it and הקדש hekdesh, gets the money because
it's completely out of my hands.
And you have a timeframe which he can do it?
Well, practically we would try, but anyway, anyway we would give preference
to the בעלים be'alim because they add a חומש, chomesh, so we'd
rather בעלים be'alim would redeem it. או דילמא, o dilma, or do
we say, so therefore do we say it's out of my hands
and once it's out of my hands I can't derive benefit, it's
like הקדש hekdesh and anybody can redeem? או דילמא, o dilma, or
do we say, כיון דקני ליה ביני ביני, keivan de-kane leh be-beinei
beinei, לא דמי להקדש. lo dami le-hekdesh. Since the owner at least
gets, remember what I get, I have a benefit in my donkey
even if I have to redeem it, even if I can't get
benefit, what? That when I redeem it with a sheep of lesser
value, I profit the difference. Right, that's why we said I could
even, you know, in theory give this donkey to a woman... and
marry her with it because it's an object of value although it's
forbidden in benefit. Why does it have value? Because it has the
potential of being redeemed at less than its value and therefore I
actually have a monetary value, an interest in my donkey. And since
I have that, therefore you don't have rights to it. It's not
completely out of my hands. I'm going to get some benefit from
this donkey once I redeem it. So that's our question. So let's
take a look.
One minute. לא דמי להקדש. lo dami lehekdesh. Therefore it's not like
הקדש. hekdesh אמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman. said Rav Nachman: תא שמע
Ta shema come and hear. הגונב פטר חמור של חברו Hagonev peter
chamor shel chaveiro
if somebody steals somebody else's firstborn donkey, משלם תשלומי כפל לבעלים meshalem
tashlumei khefel l'ba'alim he pays the owners double because even though it's
forbidden in benefit, as we see, you still have some value in
it. They stole something of yours that has value and therefore they
pay you double. Right? That's
the הלכה לגנב. halacha l'ganav. ואף על פי שגנב v'af al pi
sheganav they stole, burgled,
burgled. Anyway, ואף על פי שאין לו עכשיו v'af al pi she'ein
lo achshav although the owner has no benefit in this donkey right
now, יש לו לאחר מכאן yesh lo l'achar mikan he'll have benefit
later, and therefore it's an object of value of his, and therefore
the burglar has to pay double. So מן who is that going
like? אילימא לרבי שמעון Ilima l'Rabbi Shimon if it's Rabbi Shimon, אמאי
אין לו עכשיו amai ein lo achshav what do you mean even
though the owner has no value in this donkey? According to Rabbi
Shimon you can derive benefit in your donkey before you've redeemed it.
So of course you have value. אלא פשיטא רבי יהודה Ela peshita
Rabbi Yehuda it must be that it's Rabbi Yehuda. ואי סלקא דעתך
להקדש מדמינן ליה v'i salka daitach l'hekdesh medaminan lei
so if it's Rabbi Yehuda it's saying like this. Rabbi Yehuda says
I own this donkey, it has no, I can't derive benefit now,
but I still have value in it because I could redeem it
and profit the difference. So somebody comes ahead and steals it, they've
stolen something of mine that has actual value, and therefore they have
to pay me double. An interesting question would be: do they pay
me double the price of the donkey or double the difference between
the donkey and the sheep? But that's not our issue right now.
Our point is like this. So you see according to Rabbi Yehuda
somebody steals it, he pays me double. Now the fact that he's
paying me double shows that I am considered to be the owner
of it and it's not like הקדש hekdesh. or some other entity
is the owner of this donkey. So let's take a look.
אלא פשיטא רבי יהודה ואי סלקא דעתך להקדש מדמינן ליה ela peshita
Rabbi Yehuda v'i salka daitach l'hekdesh medaminan lei if you were to
say we were to compare it to הקדש hekdesh. this when it's
forbidden
in benefit, מביתו של איש אמר רחמנא ולא מבית הקדש. mibeito shel
ish amar rachmana v'lo mibeit hekdesh. The Torah says that you only
pay double, it says if you steal from the house of the
man, not from הקדש. hekdesh. So therefore, if it were הקדש, hekdesh,
besides that I shouldn't be getting the money at all because I
wouldn't be considered the owner, maybe he pays me the money because
he indirectly causes me a loss, but certainly I don't get double.
Double, we say, is only when the object is not owned by
הקדש, hekdesh, only when the object is totally owned by a lay
person. And therefore, if this were compared to הקדש, hekdesh. you would
not be getting double. ותו לא מידי v'tu lo midi meaning nothing,
there's nothing more to say about this. It's very clear that it's
not like הקדש and of course the other conclusion would have been
hard to imagine how that could have ever worked in any real
society. So the הלכה is yes, if Michael wants to redeem my
donkey and give the כהן Kohen, his sheep, he's more than welcome
to. Thank you for doing that מצוה mitzvah for me and for
saving me the money, but I'm sorry you don't get my donkey.
Okay? It was my donkey to begin with, and it remains my
donkey. I always could have gotten benefit from it having redeemed it.
I had a monetary right in it. He doesn't get it. But
again, what is fascinating is that the גמרא is comparing it to
הקדש because again, it's not really like it. First of all, it
doesn't have sanctity. I mean, that's the question we actually asked at
the beginning of the פרק. perek. Do we even use the term
קדושה kedusha when you talk about donkey? Even if it's forbidden in
benefit, that doesn't necessarily... if it's forbidden in benefit, it could be
an expression of קדושה, kedusha, but it's not necessarily. Right? There are
a lot of things that are forbidden in benefit that are not
קדוש. kadosh. Right? חמץ. chametz. So first of all, do you even
use the concept of קדושה? kedusha? But number two, it's not like
classic הקדש. First of all, it's not owned by the בית המקדש.
Second of all, when you redeem it, the thing you redeem it
with does not get its status. The thing you redeemed it with
is totally, has no status to it. So it is interesting that
the גמרא makes this comparison. Number one, to allow you to redeem
with value without a sheep, and that is a very practical הלכה.
And number two,
to start then even going further saying somebody else could redeem it
for me. We had never heard of that idea. And even though
we allow that, we still... you know, we suggest taking it even
further than that and saying that the person might be able to
get it after you redeem it. There we finally put on the
brakes. And there we said, no, no, no, it's not really הקדש.
Okay, maybe we make certain comparisons to say value, somebody else can
do it, but we're not actually saying its status is הקדש. If
its status was something like הקדש, you wouldn't have this הלכה about
paying double. So clearly that's not what's going on, although some comparisons
tell us that you redeem with value and that somebody else can
do it. Okay, now to move on. Yes.
This is a bit... so if someone does actually steal from הקדש,
then you have מעילה issues, right? You bring a קרבן korban and
he has to... What is it? No, but wouldn't you get כרת
karet for it if you...
what's that for? If you actually derive הנאה. hana'ah. If you actually
take it without deriving הנאה, hana'ah, and if you did it במזיד,
b'meizid, then you wouldn't get מעילה קרבן. me'ilah korban. Anyway, but let's
not... when we get to בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, we can talk
about stealing from הקדש. Okay. אחת ביכרה ואחת שלא ביכרה. achat bikra
v'achat shelo bikra. Now we get into the case where one animal
gave birth... had already given birth already, one and not, you don't
know this, and then it had a male and a female, you
don't know which came from which. Anyway, a classic example about which
is a doubtful... you have a doubt whether you're obligated to give
a firstborn, is this really firstborn or not, and you give, you
separate out one sheep and you keep it for yourself. Okay, so
to remove the forbidden nature of the of the donkey. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan.
Then the end of that משנה said that you give מעשר בהמה
Ma'aser Behemah from these sheep that you redeemed with the donkey. So
what is the scenario where you give מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah with
sheep you that you used for the redemption? Let's take a look.
כיצד אמרו נכנס לדיר להתעשר? Keitzad amru nichnas le-dir le-his'aser?
How do they say that you bring them all into the pen
to take מעשר? Ma'aser? אי אתה יכול לומר בבא לידי כהן. Ee
atah yachol lomar be-va lidei Kohen. You can't say if the כהן
Kohen got ten first ten sheep for his instead of donkeys, whatever,
for the redemption, he got ten sheep that he now takes these
sheep and gives מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah on it. Why not? שהרי
שנינו הלוקח ושניתן לו במתנה. She-harei shaninu ha-loke'ach ve-she-nitan lo be-matanah. If
you purchase a sheep or you receive sheep in as a gift,
פטור ממעשר בהמה. patur mi-Ma'aser Behemah. You don't give מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser
Behemah. מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah is only for the sheep
that are born or the calves that are born in your flock.
Okay, so it has to be something that is born to you,
not stuff that you purchased. So we cannot be talking that the
sheep were given to the כהן, Kohen, then מעשר Ma'aser would not
be relevant.
Does a כהן Kohen give מעשר Ma'aser to himself? What? I'm sorry,
what's the question?
It doesn't matter. No, you have to be מפריש mafrish it off
and bring it as a קרבן Korban and so on. מעשר Ma'aser
actually has קדושה. kedushah. But a כהן, Kohen. if he has firstborn
sheep he would, but he isn't but if they're not firstborn, if
he has newly born sheep he would, but this is not born
to him.
He received it from the ישראל. Yisrael. So you do not bring
מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah from stuff you receive from someone else. Only
from stuff that is born into your flock. Okay.
So, אלא בישראל. Ella be-Yisrael. So here's the scenario. It's a it's
a ישראל, Yisrael, a Jew, שהיו לו עשרה ספק פטרי חמורים בתוך
ביתו. she-hayu lo asarah safek pitrei chamorim be-toch beiso. He had ten
doubtful firstborn donkeys in his house, שמפריש עליהן עשרה שיין, she-mafrish aleihen
asarah seiyin,
and he separates out ten sheep to be in their substitute. But
what do we say? You separate out a sheep and get to
keep it. Now I'll remind you that רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam said
that if you had many doubtful donkeys, you could use the same
sheep to redeem multiple times since the כהן Kohen. isn't getting it
anyway. תוספות Tosafos points out that this גמרא is obviously difficult with
רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. It sounds like for each doubtful donkey you
need to do a different sheep to use in redemption. But תוספות
Tosafos says, well, maybe the גמרא is just saying that that's what
you happened to do, not that you have to do that. But
it says you happened to do that because it wants to dig
to discuss the following scenario. Okay.
Who keeps the donkey the sheep you said?
If it's a doubtful redemption, then you keep the sheep.
So what are you actually doing?
Why are you redeeming it? Because like we said, because the otherwise
the donkey, if it were firstborn, would be forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah.
So on the possibility that it might be firstborn, you don't want
you want to be allowed to use your donkey, so you redeem
it. But because you can't prove that it was firstborn, you get
to keep the sheep afterwards.
But so you go through some kind of ceremony?
Right. You say, this sheep is in in case this donkey is
a firstborn, I am redeeming it with this sheep, and now I'm
just going to and end of story. Then I then I use
the sheep use the donkey.
Okay. So, so it says, so what do you do? מפריש עליהן
עשרה שיין ומעשרן והן שלו. Mafrish aleihen asarah seiyin u-ma'asran ve-hen shelo.
So now you take מעשר. Ma'aser. Now you have these ten sheep,
they're all yours, they were all born to you newly this year,
you get to keep them, but you still take מעשר Ma'aser on
them. So when it says you take מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behemah, it
means that when you redeem the sheep and didn't give it to
the כהן, Kohein. the fact that it was redeemed does not get
you out of מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behemah, because you could imagine somebody
trying to argue like this, saying, listen, I'm not giving it to
the כהן Kohein. because he can't prove that it's his. But it
might be his. And since it might be his, then it's not
mine, and I don't have to give מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah on
it. So we say, I'm sorry, if you're keeping it, then על
פי ממון al pi mamon it's still yours, and על פי ממון
al pi mamon it's still yours, and it was born to you,
not firstborn, newly born to you, although it's not the firstborn animal,
and therefore you still give מעשר בהמה Ma'aser Behemah off of these
sheep. So that's what our משנה means. Now the גמרא goes on,
מסייע ליה לרב נחמן. Mesayei lei le-Rav Nachman. This supports רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, De-amar Rav Nachman
amar Rabbah bar Avuha, ישראל שהיו לו עשרה ספק פטרי
חמורים. Yisrael she-hayu lo asarah safek pitrei chamorim. Now if a if
a Jew had ten doubtful firstborn donkeys, מפריש עליהן עשרה שיין, mafrish
aleihen asarah seiyin, you separate out ten sheep, ומעשרן, u-ma'asran, and you
still take מעשר Ma'aser because you're keeping the sheep and they're sheep
that are born to you that year, so you take מעשר Ma'aser
off of it and you know the tenth one is מעשר בהמה
Ma'aser Behemah and brought as a קרבן. Korban. והן שלו, Ve-hen shelo,
and you keep them all. Okay.
ואמר רב נחמן, Ve-amar Rav Nachman, so he said exactly that point
that we had in our ברייתא. Beraisa. ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה, Ve-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, the same רב
נחמן said in the name of רבה בר אבוה, Rabbah bar Avuha,
ישראל שהיו לו עשרה פטרי חמורים ודאין. Yisrael she-hayu lo asarah pitrei
chamorim vada'in.
Now we're going to go from the case of doubtful to a
case of ודאי, vadai, but have it interesting in the following way.
A Jew had ten definite firstborn donkeys בתוך ביתו, be-toch beiso, and
he had them in his house. Now, how'd he get them?
שנפלו מבית אבי אמו כהן. She-naflu mi-beis avi imo Kohen. His grandfather
on his mother's side was a כהן. Kohein Right, you understand that
when you go to grandfather you can switch כהן ישראל Kohen Yisrael
because it's on your mother's side. Okay, so his grandfather on his
mother's side was a כהן. Kohein? So, now how did his grandfather
on his mother's
side... ואותו אבי אמו כהן, ve'oso avi imo Kohein, that paternal grandfather,
נפלו לו מבית אבי אמו ישראל. nafelu lo mibeis avi imo Yisroel.
His maternal grandfather, who was a ישראל, Yisroel, had ten firstborn donkeys.
So you get it? You go to the great-great-grandfather that was a
ישראל. Yisroel. He had ten firstborn donkeys. He was supposed to redeem
them and give them to a כהן. Kohein What happened? He went
ahead and he died on us, okay, and his son died. And
anyway, then the grandfather inherited these ten firstborn donkeys. Now, the grandfather
was a כהן. Kohein. Now, if a כהן Kohein, has firstborn donkeys,
what does our first mishnah teach? חייב או פטור chayav o patur
in firstborn donkeys to give it to a כהן? Kohein, פטור, patur,
right? A כהן Kohein, and a לוי Levi are exempt from giving
their firstborn donkeys to a כהן. Kohein. So the grandfather got these
firstborn donkeys. Although in the hands of his grandfather it was חייב
chayav to be given, now that he inherits it, the status changes
and it's exempt to be given. Now he dies, this כהן, Kohein,
and it goes to his grandson, who's a ישראל. Yisroel. Does it
once again become obligated to be given, or do we say since
my grandfather, although my great-great-grandfather was obligated, since my grandfather was exempt,
I remain exempt?
That's the question. I would assume I remain exempt. Anyway, these donkeys
are now alive like 150 years.
Let's not ask those trivial questions. Okay, וזה vezeh it was just
done of the great-great-grandfather, all of these people were all alive at
the same time.
It's just there was a lot of deaths that one year, but
the great-great-grandfather and the grandfather. Okay. Anyway, so that's what the גמרא
is going to say. So let's take a look.
Where are we? ואותו אבי אמו כהן מפריש
עליהן עשרה שייהן ומעשרן והן שלו. ve'oso avi imo Kohein mafrish aleihen
asara seiyin umasran vehen shelo. You separate out ten sheep and keep
them. Now, why do you have to separate out ten sheep? Presumably,
they're forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. Presumably, that status doesn't change. So in
order to change to get them not forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, you
have to do the act of redemption. But in terms of an
obligation to give the sheep to a כהן, Kohein. since it's coming
through your grandfather who was exempt, you also by the fact that
it was exempt... Mattered what? The great-great-grandfather they were forbidden in הנאה.
hana'ah. So they don't stop being forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, so they
still have to be redeemed. But in terms of the מצוה mitzvah
then of giving to a כהן, Kohein that doesn't apply because it
went past through the grandfather who would be exempt from giving it
to a כהן. Kohein Okay. ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה.
ve'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha. We're going to have another
case just like this. ישראל, Yisroel, and the גמרא שהיו לו טבלים
ממורחים בתוך ביתו. shehayu lo tevalim memurachim betoch beito. A ישראל, Yisroel,
a non-כהן, Kohein
has טבל tevel that has been, you know, that has done מירוח,
meiruach, which is like it's been smoothed out in the heap of
grain, which means that it's obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'ma'asros. Now
they're in his house. Where did he get this from? שנפלו לו
מבית אבי אמו כהן. shenafelu lo mibeis avi imo Kohein. His grandfather
on the maternal side, on his mother's side, was a כהן. Kohein.
Now, why is that relevant? As opposed to the firstborn donkey. Firstborn
donkey, a כהן Kohein, is completely exempt, okay. A כהן Kohein, is
not exempt giving תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros from his own grain. But
what is similar is while he has to separate out תרומות ומעשרות,
terumos u'ma'asros, what's a כהן Kohen allowed to do after he separates
out תרומות ומעשרות? terumos u'ma'asros? Keep it. So what's similar is, it's
actually very if you think about it structurally similar because here too,
you needed to redeem it with a sheep, you had to remove
the forbidden status. But once it was redeemed with the sheep, you're
allowed to keep it if you're a כהן. Kohen. Okay, that was
in one case. Here too, he has to separate תרומות ומעשרות, terumos
u'ma'asros, the grandfather who is a כהן, Kohen, in order to remove
the טבל tevel and forbidden status. But once that's done because he's
a כהן, Kohen. he gets to keep the תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u'ma'asros,
at least the מעשר ראשון, ma'aser rishon, okay. So ואותו אבי אמו
כהן נפלו לו מבית אבי אמו ישראל. ve'oso avi imo Kohein nafelu
lo mibeis avi imo Yisroel. And he actually got this from his
grandfather who was a ישראל. Yisroel. Now, you don't even have to
say that in this case. The only reason we're saying that is
to say that even though A, make it parallel, and B, even
though it started in the hands of somebody who was obligated, to
make it parallel in that sense. Okay, so in both cases it
started in the great-grandfather who was obligated, went to the grandfather who
was maybe obligated to do the redemption or to separate תרומות ומעשרות
terumos u'ma'asros but not obligated to give,
went to the person, the great-great-grandson, whatever, who now because he's getting
it from the person who was exempt remains exempt in the giving
himself. So it says, so what do you do in that case?
מעשרן והן שלו. masran vehen shelo. You take your תרומות ומעשרות terumos
u'ma'asros and you keep it. וצריכא. u'tzricha. You need to tell me
both cases. דאי אשמעינן קמייתא. de'i ashmeinan kamaisa. Had you just said
the first case, משום דקא מפריש וקאי. mishum deka mafrish veka'ei. There
I could say that in the hands of the grandfather, my grandfather,
it was like it was already separated out. Why? Because you know,
a donkey and a sheep, they're already like independent animals. So there,
I can say it's like it already took place and therefore it's
like my grandfather already separated it and then he would be allowed
to keep the sheep, so I'm also allowed to keep the sheep
because it's like it already happened. Okay, that I can say, which
you'll see the contrast, you'll see the contrast in a minute. אבל
הכא מתנה שלא הורמה כמי שהורמה דמי. aval hacha matanah shelo hurmah
kemi shehurmah dami. What we're saying is the reason when it passes
through my grandfather's hands I'm exempt is because it's like he already
took care of it. It's since it's through my grandfather, when it
was in my grandfather's hands, had he actually separated out the sheep,
we'd be done with it. He would keep the sheep. So it's
like he already took care of it and therefore I just sort
of, it's when I separate the sheep, it's like my grandfather already
separated it out and therefore I don't have to give it. Okay,
or when the grain passed through his hand, it's like he separated
out the תרומות ומעשרות Terumot U'Ma'asrot and then he was entitled to
keep it, and therefore he inherited it, bequeathed it to me, and
therefore it's like he already owned it and bequeathed it to me.
So basically what I have to say is when it was in
my grandfather's hand, it's like the the tax was already taken care
of. Is that easier to say by the grain or is it
easier to say by the donkeys? On the one hand, it's easier
to say by the donkeys, because by the grain there's an act
of separating them out, of taking ten percent, of measuring it, by
the donkey you have a donkey walking around and a sheep walking
around and you just say this is that, it's more like there's
not like an act of separation. So it's easier to say it's
like it already happened. Whereas maybe by the grain I would not
say that. מתנה שלא הורמה כמי שהורמה דמי, Matana shelo hurma k'mi
shehurma dami, as long as they haven't been separated, I can't say
it's as if they've been separated. אימא לא, Eima lo, so I
wouldn't say the grandfather exempts me. ואי אשמעינן בהא, V'ei ashmeinan beha,
had it just said it in the case of the grain,
דאפשר לעשורי מיניה וביה, De'efshar l'asuri minei u'vei, maybe it's easier to
consider by the grain like it was already done, because you use
the very selfsame grain itself, all the product is there. So even
though you need to do an act of separation, but it's all
the potential is present in the grain itself. דהא מנח, De'ha manach,
it's all in front of you. אבל התם, Aval hatam, by the
the sheep and the donkey, כיון דמעלמא בעי איתויי, Keivan d'mealma ba'ei
ayitu'ei, since it's a sheep that's not related to this donkey, maybe
I don't even own any sheep, so it's not like the whole
potential of redemption is already present within the donkey. ומפרק וקאי, U'mifrak
v'ka'i, and then I have to separate it, אימא לא, Eima lo,
maybe I can't say it's already done, צריכא, Tzricha, I need it.
So basically although we rule both cases, there's a חידוש chiddush and
the logic of why I'm exempt when it passes through my grandfather's
hands is because it's as if since he could have separated it
and kept it, it's as if he did it, and therefore I'm
entitled to keep it when I separate as well. I still have
to separate it or redeem it because it has a forbidden status,
but then I'm entitled to keep it. Yes.
Wait, wouldn't you just think that if I was a כהן Kohen.
and I had תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot U'Ma'asrot, תרומה Terumah you get to
keep but the מעשר Ma'aser was supposed to go to the לוי.
Levi.
No, so I didn't, so if you remember we've talked before about
how after the לויים Levi'im didn't come up with עזרא, Ezra, they
they fined the לויים Levi'im and they certainly allowed you or maybe
even required you to give the מעשר, Ma'aser, מעשר ראשון
Ma'aser
Rishon to the כהן.
kohen? Okay. אמר רבי שמואל בר נתן אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi
Shmuel bar Natan amar Rabbi Chanina, הלוקח טבלים מרוחין. Halokeiach tevalim meruchin.
You let's say you buy winnowed
טבל, tevel, not winnowed, whatever, whatever, smoothed over טבל, tevel, meaning but
it's now obligated in תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot U'Ma'asrot, מן העובד כוכבים, min
ha'oved kochavim, from a non-Jew, מעשרן והן שלו. me'asran v'hen shelo. So
you take מעשר Ma'aser but you get to keep it. Now why
do you get to keep it? Meaning even if you're a non-כהן,
kohen? you separate out your תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot U'Ma'asrot, obviously you, טבל
tevel has to, you have to remove the status of טבל, tevel,
you have to separate תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot U'Ma'asrot, but you don't have
to give it to a כהן. kohen, Now you can't eat תרומה,
Terumah, but you can sell it to a כהן. kohen You at
least are the monetary owner of this תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot U'Ma'asrot. Now
why? Because the גמרא is going to say wait a minute, make
up your mind. If the fact that the non-Jew owned it exempts
you, don't take it at all. If it didn't exempt you, then
you have to take it and give it. What's the middle status?
So the גמרא says, the גמרא says דמרוחינהו מאן? D'miruchinhu man? Who
first of all smoothed over the pile of grain? דיהא מרוחינהו, D'yehei
miruchinhu, which is what creates the set, which is what's the stage
of obligation of the grain of תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot U'Ma'asrot. אילימא דמרוחינהו
עובד
כוכבים, Eilima d'miruchinhu oved kochavim, if it was the non-Jew, דגנך רחמנא
ולא דגן עובד כוכבים, Degancha Rachmana v'lo degan oved kochavim, it says
your grain, not the grain of the non-Jew, which according to one
דרשה drasha means that you have to be the one to actually
make it into a heaped up pile and smooth it over, and
that's and only if a Jew does that does it become obligated,
not if a non-Jew. So then you would be totally exempt. אלא
דמרוחינהו ישראל, Ella d'miruchinhu Yisrael, then it must be that the Jew
smoothed it over and therefore the Jew, and presumably owned it when
he did that, although רש"י Rashi says even as a hired hand
of a non-Jew, תוספות Tosafot says if you're a hired hand, it's
like the non-Jew did it. So anyway, so let's say the Jew
purchased it and then did the smoothing over, so it became obligated.
But now we still have to decide if it's obligated or not
because if it grew in the hands of the non-Jew, shouldn't that
exempt it? So the גמרא says וברשות עובד כוכבים מעשרן, U'virshut oved
kochavim me'asran, and he still has to take מעשר Ma'aser even though
it's coming וברשות עובד כוכבים u'virshut oved kochavim in the possession of
the non-Jew, he took him from purchased it from the non-Jew, מעשרן.
me'asran. Now why do you have to take מעשר, Ma'aser, didn't didn't
it grow in the hands of a non-Jew? No, דאין קניין לעובד
כוכבים בארץ ישראל להפקיע מיד מעשר. De'ein kinyan l'oved kochavim b'Eretz Yisrael
l'hafki'ah miyad ma'aser. We'll have to assume that non-Jewish ownership does not
change the status of of the land of Israel, does not exempt
the grain from תרומות ומעשרות. Terumot U'Ma'asrot. That is of course the
key question in היתר מכירה, Heter Mechira, can you say if you
sold the land to a non-Jew, does it change its status for
the agricultural מצוות? mitzvot? So it is saying we're going to assume
the following. Number one, the non-Jew owning it does not change its
status for תרומות ומעשרות, Terumot U'Ma'asrot, so it grew in the hands
of a non-Jew it's still obligated. The non-Jew smoothing it and making
the pile would exempt it, but that's not what happened, he first
sold it to the Jew and the Jew smoothed it over. Fine,
so now the Jew has this grain. obligated in תרומות ומעשרות, terumos
u-maasros, why does he get to keep it? Why does he get
to
then sell it back to a כהן? kohen? Why doesn't he have
to give it to a כהן? kohen. So the גמרא says והן
שלו. vehein shelo. Why does he get to keep it? כי אמר
ליה, ki amar leh, he can say to the כהן, kohen קאתינא
מכוח גברא דלא מצית לאשתעויי דינא בהדיה. kaatina mi-koach gavra de-la mazit
le-ishtauei dina bahadeih.
This is a quite fascinating claim. He says, I am getting this
through a person who you would never have been able to bring
to a בית דין. Beis Din. If the, if the non-Jew had
not sold it to me and you would have gone to the
non-Jew and you would have said the grain is obligated in תרומות
ומעשרות terumos u-maasros and you have to give it to me, the
non-Jew would have slammed the door in your face. Nobody's obligating him
to come to a בית דין Beis Din and to follow הלכה.
So even though the grain as an object had that חיוב, chiyuv,
you never would have been able to collect. Since I purchased it
from the non-Jew, therefore you do not have a claim against me.
Now that sounds extremely strange because it might be technically I couldn't
collect, but he was still, the כהן kohen, was still entitled to
it and just because, right, I mean it might be there are
sometimes cases that you could avoid ever having to go to court,
but that doesn't mean that על פי דין al pi din that
you're exempt, right? So that is a very sort of strange concept
but it's not unheard of in the גמרא that somehow when you
come via somebody that the person had no claim against and could
not have had a claim against, he somehow lost his right in
the process. Now the גמרא is going to modify it at the
end, but at this stage it does stand, and at the end
it's going to be a special פסוק that we learn that you're
exempt and it's not going to sound as strong as it does
here. But here it actually is a fascinating claim that if I
actually at a stage, and you can imagine there are cases like
this a lot in בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, which is basically that
a non-Jew has my field and I wouldn't be able to sort
of get it out of his hands and then he sells it
to a Jew. Can I now bring my case? Can I now
bring my case against the Jew? Because the Jew says look, when
it was in his hands you had lost your rights, so you
can't now, you have no claim against me now. Again, that seems
extremely unfair. Okay, but in the end we're going to modify it
here, but it is a concept that does come up in ש"ס.
Shas. You had a question before Shai?
I think you just answered it.
Okay, fine. So let's move on.
הא דתנן התם, ha di-tenan hatam, do you see the same thing?
Well, right, although כותא, Kusa, maybe the times the בית דין Beis
Din is ממש mamash up to the hilt, it's much more used
in the case of non-Jews. Okay, let's take a look. תנן התם,
tenan hatam, we taught over there. המפקיד פירות אצל כותי או אצל
עם הארץ, ha-mafkid peiros etzel Kusi o etzel am ha-aretz, if I
leave my fruit or grain or whatever by a עם הארץ, am
ha-aretz, somebody who is usually not careful in תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u-maasros,
or a כותי, Kusi, a Samaritan who also follows different standards. בחזקתן
למעשר ולשביעית. be-chezkasan le-maaser u-le-shevi'is. I don't have to assume, I don't
have to be concerned that they might have swapped the grain. I
put them in this room,
I have them watch the room, I can assume they're the way
I left them. Why? Because if I was concerned that they had
swapped it with their own, then their own I would have to
assume maybe hasn't had תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-maasros taken from it, or
their own maybe has קדושת שביעית, kedushas shevi'is, because they're not careful
about those things. So even though it's true that they're not careful
about those things with their own stuff, I don't have to be
concerned that they swapped my stuff with their own stuff. Okay, that's
the first rule. אבל אצל עובד כוכבים, aval etzel oved kochavim, if
I leave it by a non-Jew, then כפירותיו, ke-peirosav, I have to
treat what I left as if it were his stuff. I have
to be concerned that he might have swapped it and therefore the
same way his stuff is would be still obligated in תרומות ומעשרות,
terumos u-maasros, again assuming that stuff that grew in the hands of
a non-Jew is obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u-maasros. So even if
I gave him stuff that had all the תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-maasros
taken from it and that wasn't שמיטה, shemitta, I have to be
concerned that now he maybe swapped it with his stuff that has
all of those problematic halachic states, again assuming that non-Jewish ownership of
the land does not exempt the grain from those different laws. Okay,
so that's the basic point. The basic point is in the case
by the non-Jew I have to be concerned that it was swapped
as opposed to the case of the Samaritan and the whatever עם
הארץ. am ha-aretz. And if it's swapped, then I have to treat
it like it's his stuff, and if it's his
stuff it needs תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-maasros to be taken from it.
רבי שמעון אומר דמאי. Rabbi Shimon omer demai. רבי שמעון says you
don't have to, you don't assume definitely it's swapped, it's doubtful. So
therefore you have to treat it as if it were possibly swapped.
What's the practical difference between them?
אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, להפריש כולי עלמא לא פליגי. le-hafrish
kulei alma la peligi. They nobody disagrees that you have to separate
תרומות ומעשרות terumos u-maasros again, because if it was possible that it
was swapped, then it's grain that's טבל, tevel, that's חייב מיתה, chayav
misa, and if you, you've got to separate תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u-maasros,
you don't have a choice even if it's only a possibility. כי
פליגי, ki peligi, what's the debate?
ליתנן לכהן, lisnan le-kohen, about whether after I separate תרומות ומעשרות terumos
u-maasros do I have to give it to a כהן? kohen תנא
קמא סבר ודאי חלופי. tanna kamma savar vadai chalufi. The תנא קמא
tanna kamma holds we have to, we have to assume that the
non-Jew definitely swapped them, which is a pretty amazing assumption. I mean
why would I assume that anyway? But if it was definitely swapped,
then after I separate out תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u-maasros, ובעי למיתנינהו לכהן,
u-ba'ei le-misnin'hu le-kohen, I have to give it to the כהן. kohen
ורבי שמעון סבר, ve-Rabbi Shimon savar, דמאי, demai, it's only doubtful and
therefore you separate it out but then you get to keep it.
You don't eat the תרומה, teruma, but you can sell the תרומה
teruma to a כהן kohen because he can't prove that you're really
obligated. Okay, so that all makes sense, except that it doesn't because
the first step that if the... If it was definitely swapped, you
separate it and give it to a כהן kohen *Kohen* goes against
what we just said. We just said if it came via a
non-Jew, you separate it and you get to keep it. Right? So
isn't that exactly this case? It came via a non-Jew, I separated,
I should be able to keep it. So let's take a look.
יוסף בר דימי וקמי דהך שמעתא *Yosef bar Dimi v'kamay d'hach shemata*,
רב דימי *Rav Dimi* was sitting and telling over this discussion. אמר
ליה אביי *Amar lei Abaye*, אביי *Abaye* said to him, טעמא דמספקא
ליה *tama d'mesafk'la*, the only reason you get to keep it in
that case of swapping is there's a doubt that maybe it wasn't
swapped. אי חפינו לא חפינו *ee chafinu lo chafinu*, maybe it was,
maybe it wasn't swapped. הא ודאי חפינו *ha vaday chafinu*, if it
was definitely swapped, דכולי עלמא בעי למצפיינו לכהן *de'kulei alma ba'ei l'mitsfyanu
l'Kohen*, everybody would agree that you have to separate and give it
to a כהן kohen. *Kohen*. How could that be? ואמר רב שמואל
אמרי דרבי חנינא הלוקח טבל מן העובד כוכבים ומורחין *V'amar Rav Shmuel
amarei d'Rabbi Chanina ha'lokeach tevel min ha'akum umorcheinu*, if you buy—didn't רב
שמואל *Rav Shmuel* say in the name of רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina*
that if you take טבל *tevel* from a non-Jew that has been
heaped and smoothed over and is obligated in תרומות ומעשרות *Terumos u'Maaseros*,
מעשרן והן שלו *ma'asrun v'hein shelo*, that you take מעשר *ma'aser* but
you get to keep it because if it comes via a non-Jew,
you are allowed to monetarily keep possession of it.
So we got a real problem. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, oh,
maybe there's a difference. And maybe it's a much more limited law
about when you get to keep it when it comes through a
non-Jew. דילמא כאן בתרומה גדולה כאן בתרומת מעשר *Dilma kan b'terumah gedolah
kan b'terumas ma'aser*, maybe there's a difference between regular תרומה *Terumah* and
תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. And actually the bigger question is also מעשר
*Ma'aser*, but it's going to seem like that the only case where
we say that you get to keep it if it came through
a non-Jew is a special case of תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. No
longer is it this general idea that since you couldn't bring the
non-Jew to court, you can't get it out of my hands either.
No, no, no. It's a special exemption by תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*,
which is a very tiny percentage. תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser* is a
מעשר *ma'aser* that the לויים *Levi'im* give. It's a tenth of a
tenth. It's 1%. So now, as opposed to applying to all of
the gifts, it only applies to תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*, which is
1%. Let's take a look. Okay, that you get to keep. That,
if it comes through a non-Jew, you don't have an obligation for.
So when did they say before you had no obligation, although they
seemed to make it as a very blanket statement? Now we're going
to say, uh-uh, that's only about תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. Here where
we say whether it's swapped, not swapped, if it was definitely swapped
you have to give it even though it came through a non-Jew,
that's by everything else.
Only תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser* and מעשרן והן שלו *ma'asrun v'hein shelo*,
no, even with that, you still give it, you just get to
keep it.
Only in a doubtful case. But if it was a definite case,
you have to give it to the כהן kohen *Kohen* even though
it came through a non-Jew. Okay, so the only case that you're
exempt, that the non-Jew exempts you coming through his hands is תרומת
מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. Let's take a look. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, so
he says so that's what אביי *Abaye* suggested to רב דימי *Rav
Dimi*. So רב דימי *Rav Dimi* said, one minute, or is it
the other way, who said it to who? One minute.
So דילמא *dilma*... okay, so and maybe it's—maybe that's what רב דימי
*Rav Dimi* said to אביי *Abaye*, then אביי *Abaye* said back, I'm
getting a little confused here, who says—anyway, sounds like אביי *Abaye* is
saying back, אתרן ואמרת לי *aturon v'amart li*, oh, you remind me
of something. דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי *D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*,
רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* said, מניין ללוקח טבל
ומורחין מן העובד כוכבים שפטור מתרומת מעשר *minayin la'lokeach tevel umorcheinu min
ha'akum she'patur mi'terumas ma'aser*, how do you know when you buy טבל
*tevel* from a non-Jew and now you separate it out that you're
exempt from תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*? Only תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. שנאמר
*Shene'emar*, the verse says, ואל הלויים תדבר *v'el ha'Levi'im tedaber*, speak to
the לויים *Levi'im*, ואמרת אליהם כי תקחו מאת בני ישראל *ve'amarta aleihem
ki tikchu mei'eis Bnei Yisrael*, when you take from the children of
Israel, then you should give a מעשר מן המעשר *ma'aser min ha'ma'aser*.
טבל שאתה לוקח מבני ישראל אתה מפריש מהן *Tevel she'ata lokeach mi'Bnei
Yisrael ata mafrish meihen*, when you take from grain from the Israelites,
then you separate out a מעשר *ma'aser* from a מעשר *ma'aser*, תרומת
מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*, ונתתון לכהן *v'nesatun l'Kohen*, you give it to a
כהן kohen *Kohen*. טבל שאתה לוקח מן העובד כוכבים *Tevel she'ata lokeach
min ha'akum*, when you take it from a non-Jew, אי אתה מפריש
ממנו תרומת מעשר ונתתון לכהן *ee ata mafrish mimenu Terumas Ma'aser v'nesatun
l'Kohen*, you do not have to give תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. Of
course, the problem with this is that it says מעשרן והן שלו
*ma'asrun v'hein shelo*, right? You shouldn't even have to take the תרומת
מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. It should have just said, don't take תרומת מעשר
*Terumas Ma'aser*. So maybe, you know, maybe—and here does become the interesting
point also, and also are we totally giving up on the idea
of what do you call it? Of אתינא מכוח גברא *atina
mikoch gavra*, that the fact that it came through the non-Jew is
what exempts me? So תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* says the point is like
this: the פשט *pshat* of the פסוק *pasuk* means that if for
some reason the non-Jew was being a צדיק *tzaddik* and he gave
the מעשר *ma'aser* to the לוי *Levi*, remember the grain is obligated,
that's what the פסוק *pasuk* is talking about, that if a non-Jew
gives the מעשר *ma'aser* to the לוי *Levi*, then the לוי *Levi*
does not have to take תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. So when I
get it from the non-Jew, that's why, coming via somebody that's exempt,
but now exempt not just because you know he doesn't listen to
your laws and you can't force him into בית דין *Beis Din*,
exempt that the non-Jew in principle is exempt from—his grain is exempt
from תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*. And I get it through him, then
even when I separate it out, I remain exempt. Okay, maybe that's
why I also have to do the separating. Maybe if it came
straight from the non-Jew, what it may be through me, it's a
little bit unclear at the conclusion whether I really have to do
the separating or not. But what's important for us is that number
one, this whole law is limited just to תרומת מעשר *Terumas Ma'aser*,
just based on a verse, and it's not just because you cannot
technically force the non-Jew to come to court, it's because in principle...
the non-Jew's grain is exempt from תרומת מעשר and in that way
it is very structurally similar to what we said before about the
donkeys coming via the כהן, kohen right? Where there too fundamentally they're
exempt and therefore when I get it from my grandfather I still
have to in parallel do the act of redeeming with a sheep
to remove the status but I remain exempt from giving. Let's just
finish up till the last few lines till the משנה. ומת נהנין
u-mes nehenin if it dies you can derive benefit. Now what dies?
It can't be if the donkey dies you can derive benefit from
it because we're saying like רבי יהודה, this is the end of
the משנה, that if the donkey is forbidden in benefit. So if
it dies it remains forbidden in benefit, it wasn't redeemed. So this
must mean if the sheep dies you can get benefit. Okay, but
of course if the sheep was never a problem. So let's take
a look. דמית היכא demis heicha where did this sheep die? אילימא
דמית בי כהן ilima demis bei kohen after I'd given it to
the כהן kohen the sheep died ונהנה בו כהן ve-nehena bo kohen
it says the כהן kohen can derive benefit פשיטא of course ממונא
דידיה הוא mamona didei hu he's already taken possession of it of
course afterwards if it dies he still derives benefit. אלא דמית בי
בעלים ela demis bei baalim it died in my house after I
did the redemption but before I gave it to the כהן kohen
the sheep died on me. So ונהנה בו כהן ve-nehena bo kohen
now what the משנה is saying is is that now okay the
כהן kohen can get whatever benefit he can get out of the
sheep but I am done with my obligation of redemption right? The
same I cannot redeem on a dead sheep? No, it has to
be a live sheep. Let's say I redeemed on a live sheep
and it died before I gave it to the כהן. kohen Do
I have to say well maybe that didn't my redemption isn't finished
until I give it to the כהן kohen maybe I've got to
do it again? And it's saying no once you've redeemed it if
it died it died you know not a specific כהן kohen owns
it but the כהנים kohanim own it you're done with your act
of redemption if it died it's their sheep that died you're done
with your redemption give it to a כהן he'll get whatever benefit
he can get out of this dead sheep but you're done as
long as when it was alive when you redeemed. You're supposed to
really give it to the כהן as soon as you can right?
Yeah. Okay but anyways גמרא says הא נמי פשיטא ha nami pishita
isn't that obvious? No סלקא דעתך אמינא I might have thought כל
כמה דלא מטי לידיה לא זכה ביה kol kama dela mati lidei
lo zachah beih as long as it did not get to the
hands of the כהן he did not yet take possession of it
and if he didn't take possession of it then presumably my מצוה
of redemption my act of redemption is not complete and maybe I
have to redeem it again קא משמע לן it teaches us דבעידנא
דאפרשיה de-be-idna de-afrashei as soon as I separated it ברשותא דכהן קאי
bi-reshusa de-kohen kai the כהן has possession of it and therefore my
act of redemption is done and therefore if it died it's no
longer my headache. Once I've redeemed it and I said this sheep
for this donkey I am done. Now I'm supposed to give it
to a כהן yes but now if it dies it's not my
problem anymore. תוספות says based on this that you make a ברכה
bracha when you redeem it but you don't make a ברכה bracha
when you give it to the כהן because the giving of the
כהן is not really part of the act of redemption it's just
now handing over something that they already own. In this way also
I'm not sure you take a look על מצות al mitzvas I'm
not sure
על פדיון פטר חמור al pidyon peter chamor I don't know. Anyway
the other thing is though what's the other point? Oh to think
also that similar to what we learned at the end of חולין
Chullin about מתנות כהונה matnos kehuna right remember where they have possession
of it it's like owned by them as a collective even before
I've given it over to them so this also ends very similar
because this again is something that goes to a כהן that doesn't
have sanctity and is owned by them as a collective you know
even before it's handed over but then of course I have to
do the final step and handing it over to them. Okay and
with that we will end and we are all caught up.